<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blockchain on Dave Hudson</title>
    <link>https://hashingit.com/tags/Blockchain/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blockchain on Dave Hudson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <copyright>© 2014-2021 David J. Hudson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hashingit.com/tags/Blockchain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting real with blockchain</title>
      <link>https://hashingit.com/blog/2019-01-09-1200/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hashingit.com/blog/2019-01-09-1200/</guid>
      <description>Note 2020-03-06: An earlier, longer, version of this was published on Medium and LinkedIn. This version has been slightly edited to be a bit less of a sales pitch for my then-team, Solutions Engineering. I&amp;rsquo;m very happy to note that in the 14 months since the original article, the team has gone on to bigger and better things, continuing to help customers &amp;ldquo;get real&amp;rdquo; with Corda.
 It’s pretty-much impossible to avoid the pronouncements in both the technical and mainstream press about how blockchain is going to change the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What IoT history reveals about blockchain’s challenges</title>
      <link>https://hashingit.com/blog/2017-01-06-1400/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hashingit.com/blog/2017-01-06-1400/</guid>
      <description>Note 2020-03-06: This was originally published as an opinion piece at Coindesk.
   Cave paintings vis https://www.shutterstock.com/pic-94533745/stock-photo-famous-prehistoric-rock-paintings-of-tassili-najjer-algeria.html
  2009 saw Satoshi Nakamoto deploy the first Bitcoin node, and within five years its blockchain had become a large-scale industry.
But while new applications and commercial opportunities seemed only a short step away, in 2016, we realized that industrial blockchains weren’t going to be so straightforward.
Early enthusiasm for new technologies is nothing new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blockchain, what art thou?</title>
      <link>https://hashingit.com/blog/2015-12-30-0000/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hashingit.com/blog/2015-12-30-0000/</guid>
      <description>As we approach 2016 there seem to be endless discussions about &amp;ldquo;blockchain&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a term that is ever-more frequently cited in even mainstream journalism, while in the fintech space alone there are a slew of would-be suppliers and would-be users claiming that &amp;ldquo;blockchain&amp;rdquo; will revolutionize any number of applications. This now-common usage suggests it must be something precisely defined and well understood, but this seems to be more a matter of mantra than comprehension.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
