<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Musings of an Itinerant Software Designer</title>
    <link>https://dave-hudson.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Musings of an Itinerant Software Designer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2020 David J. Hudson</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 21:40:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://dave-hudson.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Making this site work for real (AKA I hate Git submodules)</title>
      <link>https://dave-hudson.github.io/posts/2020-01-24-2140/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 21:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dave-hudson.github.io/posts/2020-01-24-2140/</guid>
      <description>So I think I typed too soon yesterday. Git submodules may be tolerable to some people but after another hour wasted on them today it&#39;s time to admit defeat and find another path. It turns out that putting the publication directory at the same level as the source directory for this site then it&#39;s easy make things work. All it takes is putting ../ in publishDir and we&#39;re ok :-)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making this site work</title>
      <link>https://dave-hudson.github.io/posts/2020-01-23-1800/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 18:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dave-hudson.github.io/posts/2020-01-23-1800/</guid>
      <description>One of the more fun things about setting up this site (or at least fun for me!) is getting to have vim open again, and being able to see how my words will properly be marked up and translated. I guess it makes me remember what it is to be someone who does this day in and out (organising teams of engineers is fun, but I do miss building code sometimes).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Episode IV: A new blog</title>
      <link>https://dave-hudson.github.io/posts/2020-01-22-2230/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 22:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dave-hudson.github.io/posts/2020-01-22-2230/</guid>
      <description>A number of times in the past I&#39;ve found myself wanting to blog about some of the things I&#39;ve been reading about, thinking about, or working on. Somehow, though, I&#39;ve never managed to make the habit stick.
I think part of the problem is that I will always be a software developer at heart and prepackaged, WYSIWYG, tools that have limited flexibility never quite appealled to me (that and disliking the bloaty databases and slow rendering behind most of them).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wiki</title>
      <link>https://dave-hudson.github.io/wiki/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 22:20:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dave-hudson.github.io/wiki/</guid>
      <description>When I&#39;ve had a little more time this part of the site will collect interesting things into one place. When it does you may have an irresistible urge to browse the content, but in the meantime I&#39;ll just let you imagine what that might be like!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Dave Hudson</title>
      <link>https://dave-hudson.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 21:09:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dave-hudson.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Dave (apparently always pictured with a drink!)   Hello, good morning/afternoon/evening* and welcome! (*please delete as appropriate)
I&#39;m a unrepentant geek who loves all things engineering, scientific or otherwise techie. I would say I love maths too, but I should probably leave that to the experts :-)
I&#39;ve been playing with computers and writing software since I was 9 which is way more years than I care to think about.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>